<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Two solemne covenants made between God and man: viz. [brace] the covenant of workes, and the covenant of grace. [brace] Clearly laid open, distinguished, and vindicated from many dangerous opinions; the right knowledge of which [sic] will be very profitable to all those that have escaped the first, and are confirmed in the second at the Sacrament. January 15. 1646. Imprimatur. John Downame.</title>
            <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79028</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E373_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201327</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861851</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113996</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79028)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113996)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 59:E373[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Two solemne covenants made between God and man: viz. [brace] the covenant of workes, and the covenant of grace. [brace] Clearly laid open, distinguished, and vindicated from many dangerous opinions; the right knowledge of which [sic] will be very profitable to all those that have escaped the first, and are confirmed in the second at the Sacrament. January 15. 1646. Imprimatur. John Downame.</title>
                  <author>Calamy, Edmund, 1600-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14, [16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Banks, and are to be sold in Blackfriers at the top of Bridewell staires and in Westminster Hall at the signe of the Seale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edmund Calamy by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "feb: 1st: 1646"; the 7 in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grace (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Good works (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Two ſolemne COVENANTS MADE Between God and Man: viz.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Covenant of Workes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>And the Covenant of Grace.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Clearly laid open, diſtinguiſhed, and vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated from many dangerous opinions; the right knowledge of whch will be very profitable to all thoſe that have eſcaped the firſt, and are confirmed in the ſecond at the Sacrament.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Rom. 5.18, 19.</hi>
                  </bibl> Therefore as by the offence of one, judgement came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all men to condemnation: even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came upon all men unto juſtification of life.</p>
               <p>For as by one mans diſobedience, many were made ſinners, ſo by the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of one, ſhall many be made righteous.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 1.16.</hi>
                  </bibl> For the Law was given by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="lat" subtype="imprimatur">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>January 15. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Imprimatur.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Downame.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Banks,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Blackfriers</hi> at the top of <hi>Bridewell</hi> ſtaires and in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall</hi> at the ſigne of the Seale, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113996:2"/>
            <head>Two ſolemne Covenants made betweene God and Man, viz. the Covenant of Workes, and the Covenant of Grace, clearly laid open, diſtinguiſhed, and vindicated from many dangerous and deſtructive opinions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be ſeverall opinions about the Covenant of Works, and the Covenant of grace, to the great diſturbance of many Chriſtians; ſome hold that there be foure Covenants, two of Works, and two of Grace; the two firſt, one with <hi>Adam</hi> before the fall, and the other with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their returne out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and the Covenants of Grace the firſt to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the other at the Incarnation of Jeſus Chriſt; this M. <hi>Sympſon</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed before a Committee of the Aſsembly of Divines in my hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. 2. Others hold that there is but three Covenants; the firſt with <hi>Adam,</hi> the ſecond with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their going out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and a third with Jeſus Chriſt, the two firſt of Workes, and the laſt of Grace, and this M. <hi>Burroughes</hi> delivered in his Expoſition Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in <hi>Cornhill</hi> in my hearing. 3. Others hold that there is but two Covenants, the one of Works, and the other of Grace; yet the firſt they hold was made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at <hi>Mount Sinai,</hi> and no Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of workes before that, and now it is vaniſhed away, and the other a Covenant of grace yet not made till the death of Chriſt the teſtator, and this is affirmed by <hi>James Pope,</hi> in a Book entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>the unveiling of Antichriſt.</hi> 4. Others hold that the Law at <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> was a Covenant of grace, implying that there is more then one Covenant of grace, and this is affirmed by Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> in his Vindication of the Morall Law the 24. Lecture, text the 4. of <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> 5. Others with my ſelfe hold that there is but two Covenants, the one a Covenant of Workes, and the tree
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113996:3"/>of life, was a Sacrament or ſigne and token of it, this was made with <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall and to all his poſterity who come under it as ſoon as they take upon them his nature, for he did bear an Image for himſelfe and all his poſtetity, ſo that if he had ſtood in his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity he had conveyed his righteouſneſſe and holineſſe to all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and when he by ſin defiled his nature, the whole race of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind was polluted by him, and alſo he received a Covenant both for himſelfe and all his poſterity, and in caſe he had been faithfull to it, all his poſterity had ſtood with him, but he breaking that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant brought not only guilt upon himſelf but upon all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity with him, ſo that now there is none clean, no not one; <hi>how can he be clean that is born of a woman?</hi> Job 25.4. thus mans nature is polluted. And in regard of the Covenant, let every mouth be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, <hi>for all the world is become guilty before God,</hi> Rom. 3.29. <hi>for all have ſinned and come ſhort of the glory of God,</hi> Rom. 3.23. <hi>by one man ſinne entred into the world, and death by ſinne, and ſo death paſſed upon all men for that all have ſinned,</hi> Rom 5.12. ſo then all men by nature lye under the pollution and guilt of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, and lyable to all the curſes and penalties due unto them for breach of that Covenant.</p>
            <p>But then there was a Covenant of grace which God the Father made with Jeſus Chriſt from all eternity to ſave ſome of the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Adam,</hi> and had not this Covenant been prepared ready a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> to take place at the very moment of his fall, the Juſtice of God had immediatly ſeized upon the whole Creation under Heaven, and conſum'd them to their firſt nothing, but then came Jeſus Chriſt with the covenant in his hand ſaying, be gracious unto him, and deliver him from going down to the pit, I have found a ranſome, Job 33.24. now I ſhall prove that the covenant of grace was made with Jeſus Chriſt from all eternity, being a contract or plot of God the Father with God the Sonne from all eternity as mediator for the ſalvation of the Elect.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If God the Father promiſed eternall life before the world began when as there was no creature as yet made, this promiſe muſt needs be made to Jeſus Chriſt our mediatour? but God promiſed eternall life before the world began, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.2. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it muſt needs be made to Jeſus Chriſt our mediator before the world began.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if Jeſus Chriſt was ſet apart from all eternity for this worke, then the Covenant of grace was made with him before the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113996:3"/>world was, but ſaith <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I was ſet up from everlaſting before the earth was, when there was no depths, before the Mountaines were fetled, when he prepared the heavens, when he eſtabliſhed the clouds, when he gave the Sea his decree, then was I by him as one brought up with him, Pro. 8.23. to the 30. now this cannot be meant of Chriſt as God, for then who ſhould ſet him up or appoint him any work, then it muſt needs follow that it was Jeſus Chriſt as Mediatour with whom the Covenant of grace was made, for <hi>him hath God the Father ſealed,</hi> John 6.27.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If it was appointed before the world was, that Chriſt ſhould come and die for ſinners, then the Covenant of grace was made with him to ſave a certain number from all eternity, but ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> when that Kings and Rulers were gathered together againſt the Lord and againſt his Chriſt, it was to do what God had deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined before to be done, Acts 4.26, 27, 28. and you are redeemed with the precious blood of Chriſt as of a Lambe without ſpot or blemiſh, who verily was foreordained before the foundation of the world, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19, 20. therefore the Covenant of grace was made with Jeſus Chriſt before the world began.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if God appointed Chriſt a time, and at the fulneſſe of time he came to redeem thoſe that were under the Law that they might receive the adoption of ſonnes, then the Covenant of grace was made with Jeſus Chriſt from all eternity, but this firſt is true, Gal. 4.3.4. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond, and it further appears in that when God ſent his firſt begotten ſonne into the world he ſaith, <hi>let all the Angells of God worſhip him,</hi> Heb. 1.6. and to men he ſaith, <hi>this is my beloved ſonne heare him,</hi> Mat. 17.3.5.17. then the Covenant of grace was made with him.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If God ſay of Chriſt, behold my ſervant whom I uphold, mine elect in whom my ſoule delighteth, he ſhall bring forth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Gentiles, he ſhall not be diſcouraged till he have ſet judgement in the earth, and the Iles ſhall wait for his Law, and I will give thee for a Covenant to the people to open their eyes and to bring out the priſoners from the priſon; then the Covenant of grace muſt needs be made with Jeſus Chriſt, but the firſt is true, Iſai 42.1.4.6, 7. therefore ſo is the ſecond, and that the covenant was made with Jeſus Chriſt, ſee further, thou my ſervant ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the diſperſed of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and I will give thee a light to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113996:4"/>that thou maiſt give ſalvation unto the ends of the earth, the the Redeemer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and the holy one he ſhall chuſe thee and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thee, and give thee for a Covenant to eſtabliſh the earth, ſee Iſa. 49.6, 7, 8, 9. then the new covenant was made with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, If the Lord looked from Heaven and ſaw that there was no man to make interceſſion and then his own arme brought ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and his own righteouſneſſe it ſuſtained him, becauſe he travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the greatneſſe of his ſtrength, and is mighty to ſave, yea if God laid help upon one that is mighty, and this was Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins,</hi> Mat. 1.21. then this muſt needs be Jeſus Chriſt with whom the Covenant of grace was made, but the firſt is true from theſe Scriptures, Iſa. 59.16.63. 1. Pſa. 89.19. then it muſt needs be Jeſus Chriſt with whom the Covenant of grace was made,</p>
            <p>Seventhly, If Chriſt became our ſurety, and was bruiſed for our iniquities, and the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and by his ſtripes we are healed, then the new Covenant was made with him, but the firſt is true from theſe ſcriptures, Heb. 7.21. Iſa. 53.3.5. 1 Pet. 3.18, <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Eightly, If Chriſt be the meſſenger of the Covenant, and all the promiſes made in him, and there is no other name given by which we ſhall be ſaved, then the covenant was made with him, but the firſt is true from theſe ſcriptures, Mal. 3.1. 2 Cor. 1.20. Acts 4.12. <hi>Ergo,</hi> ſo is the ſecond.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, If God hath promiſed to Chriſt that he ſhall ſee his ſeed, and that the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand, and if we be choſen in Chriſt, adopted and accepted in Chriſt and gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together and bleſſed in him and our names written in his books of life, then the covenant was made with Chriſt, but the firſt is true from theſe Scriptures, Iſa 53.10. Ephe. 1.3, 4, 5, 6.10. Revel. 13.8. <hi>Ergo,</hi> then the covenant of grace was made with Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The next thing is to ſhew how we come to be freed from the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and the guiltineſſe of our condition wherein we are borne and do lye under the covenant of works. I anſwer, the holineſſe of Jeſus Chriſt his perſon doth ſanctifie our unholineſſe, he is called the <hi>holy child Jeſus, Acts</hi> 4.30. <hi>that holy thing, Luke</hi> 1.35. he was the ſonne of God, and he was the ſonne of Man, yet not two ſons but one ſonne of God, or one Chriſt; and though he took our nature
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113996:4"/>upon him yet not by generation from man, he was conceived by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.36. therefore not conceived and borne in ſin as we are, <hi>for their ſakes ſaith Chriſt I ſanctifie my ſelfe that they alſo might be ſanctified, John</hi> 17.19. thus by his holineſſe we become holy, as by <hi>Adams</hi> filthineſſe we became filthy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the merits of Chriſts obedience to the covenant of works he hath freed his people from the guilt of their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that covenant of works he was <hi>made under the Law to redeem them that are under the Law, Gal.</hi> 4.4, 5. now the obedience of Chriſt to the covenant of works was two-fold; Firſt, his active obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that covenant who did performe it without any ſpot of ſin, he ſaith of his obedience to his Father, I do alwaies thoſe things that pleaſe him, <hi>John</hi> 8.29. he finiſhed the work that his Father gave him to do, <hi>John</hi> 17.4. and ſaith his Father, <hi>this is my beloved ſon in whom I am well pleaſed, Mat.</hi> 3.15. thus hath the perfect obedience of Jeſus Chriſt ſatisfied for all the diſobedience of his people to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works. Secondly, The other part of Chriſts obedience was paſſive, he ſuffered the penalty due unto us for our diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to that covenant, though he were a ſon, yet learned he obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by the things which he ſuffered, and being made perfect he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the author of ſalvation to all them that obey him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.8, 9.2.10. it behoved Chriſt to ſuffer and to riſe from the dead the third day, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.26.46. Chriſt hath once ſuffered for ſins, the Juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. he that knew no ſin, neither was guile found in his mouth, who when he ſuffered he threatned not, but committed himſelfe to him that judgeth righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25. he alone trod the winepreſſe of his Fathers wrath, and there was none with him, Iſa. 63.3. he cry'd out the pains of hell gat hold of him, and he cryed out, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me,</hi> now the dignity of his perſon being both God and Man in one Chriſt, his humanity ſuffering but a ſhort time made his obedience ſo meritorious, to free us from that guilt and penalty that is due unto us for our breach of that covenant.</p>
            <p>In the next place I am to ſhew how we come to enter into this new covenant with Jeſus Chriſt, I anſwer, by faith alone, faith is that grace on our part by which we are grafted into the ſecond <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26.2.16. and ſo come into this covenant as by nature we are in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> and ſo in his covenant, ſo he that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113996:5"/>believeth in Chriſt ſhall not periſh but have eternall life; <hi>John</hi> 3.15 16. <hi>he that hath the ſon hath life,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5, 22. <hi>onely beleeve, Mark</hi> 5.36. being juſtified by faith we have peace with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. for as by the offence of <hi>Adam,</hi> judgement came upon all men in his nature to condemnation, even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, the free gift came upon all that are in him by faith unto juſtification of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. now faith uniting us unto Chriſt as the head and members, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. makes all the active and paſſive obedience of Chriſt to be ours by imputation, and likewiſe all our ſinfulneſſe and guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be his, and he coming as a ſurety takes upon him to pay all our debts, and by our matrimoniall union with him all his riches becomes ours, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. by this key of faith we fetch daily new grace out of his treaſury of grace to ſanctifie us more and more, till at laſt we have our full meaſure according to the gift of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſhewed with whom the two covenants were made, the covenant of works with <hi>Adam,</hi> a meer man, but the covenant of grace with Jeſus Chriſt both God and man, and alſo the time when they were made, one with <hi>Adam</hi> as ſoon as created, but the other with Jeſus Chriſt from all eternity; alſo I have ſhewed how all men enter into theſe two covenants, firſt, all men enter into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> covenant by nature, but the Elect only enter into Chriſts co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant by grace; alſo I have ſhewed how that <hi>Adam</hi> by his breach of covenant defil'd all his poſterity, and alſo brought guilt upon them for it, but Jeſus Chriſt ſanctifies by the holineſſe of his nature all in his covenant, and acquits them and juſtifies them from all their guilt by his active and paſſive obedience, fulfilling the covenant of works perfectly; now if all the whole race of mankind be contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in one of theſe two covenants, then it muſt needs follow that God never made any other but theſe two touching the eternall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of mankind: but I have proved that all men by nature enter into <hi>Adams</hi> covenant, ſave Jeſus Chriſt that did not come into the world by the ordinary courſe of nature, and ſo they all continue till Jeſus Chriſt free them from that covenant of works, and ſo ſtate them in the covenant of grace; therefore God never made any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther covenant touching the eternall eſtate of mankind but theſe two.</p>
            <p>Now ſome will object and ſay God made a covenant with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, Gen.</hi> 17. and another with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at their return out of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113996:5"/>Jer.</hi> 11.3, 4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13. and a third or new covenant at the death of Chriſt the teſtator, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8.10. and ſome deny the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works with <hi>Adam</hi> in the time of his creation and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace with Jeſus Chriſt made from all eternity, affirming, there was no covenant made with man before <hi>Iſraels</hi> return from <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and this they call the covenant of works, and no covenant of grace made before the death of Chriſt, and this they call the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace; now when I have anſwered theſe objections, I hope I ſhall give ſome ſatisfaction to thoſe that are troubled with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeverall opinions touching the covenant of grace and the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works made with the two <hi>Adams,</hi> repreſenting all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to the firſt objection, if God made a covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and that alſo a covenant of grace, then it will follow that God made two covenants of grace, and then we muſt have two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemers, and if one of them was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> this is to make him who ſaith he is but duſt and aſhes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. to be one of thoſe redeemers or ſaviours who was but a poor creature himſelf, but they will ſay, to <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> were the promiſes made, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. I anſwer, as one King makes a league or covenant with another by an Embaſſadour, ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> repreſented Chriſt, for the promiſe of eternall life was made before the world began, <hi>Titus</hi> 12. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore before <hi>Abraham</hi> had his being, or it may be anſwered thus: <hi>Abraham</hi> received the ſign or token of this covenant, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10, 11. when as the covenant it ſelfe was made with Chriſt from all eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and thoſe elect that fall in every age of the world ſince <hi>Adams</hi> fall God hath been in Chriſt, not in <hi>Abraham,</hi> reconciling them to himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19, 20. and if <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould ſtand for all the Elect to receive a covenant for them, then he ſhould ſtand for them with an Image alſo without ſin, to anſwer for their loſt Image by <hi>Adam;</hi> but this he could not do becauſe he was deſiled with ſin as other men, then the covenant of grace was not made with him but with Chriſt, who took upon him our nature and our infirmities and yet without ſin, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.15. ſo then <hi>Abraham</hi> received circumciſion the token of the covenant, but himſelfe was ſaved by his faith in Chriſt, for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Abraham ſaw my day and was glad, John</hi> 8.56. it was Chriſt that was given for a covenant, <hi>he is the redeemer of Iſrael that holy one, Iſa.</hi> 49.7, 8. it was Chriſts righteouſneſſe that was imputed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113996:6"/>to him and received by faith when he received the ſign of circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. and <hi>Abraham</hi> did but receive a further confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the covenant of grace made with Chriſt before the world was by the ſign of circumciſion when God took in that Nation into the viſible Church, ſo much for anſwer to this objection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> 2. Some object and ſay the Law at <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> was a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, and others ſay it was a covenant of works, but I ſhall prove that it was neither, but only given to thoſe that were in covenant as a rule of obedience, ſo runs the preface, <hi>I am the Lord thy God,</hi> that is by the covenant of grace made with Jeſus Chriſt and confirmed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> therefore <hi>thou ſhalt have none other Gods but me,</hi> and in all thoſe places where doing is required it is firſt ſaid, <hi>I am the Lord your God, therefore ye ſhall keep my Statutes and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> which if a man do, he ſhall live in them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.2.4.5. <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.1. and ſaith the Lord God <hi>in the day that I choſe Iſrael and made my ſelfe known to them in the land of Aegypt,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I am the Lord your God,</hi> then it followes, <hi>I gave them my Statutes and ſhewed them my Judgements,</hi> which if a man do <hi>he ſhall even live in them, Ezekell</hi> 20.5.11. Thus they were in covenant before the rule of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience was given, for the Law is not of faith, but the man that doth them ſhall live in them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.12. that is, he that obeyeth that rule being in the new covenant by faith in Chriſt ſhall live, yet not for his doing but for his believing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.26. it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a glaſſe to ſee their ſin, <hi>James</hi> 1.23, 24, 25. by the Law is the knowledge of ſin, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.20.7.7. it was given them as a ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter to drive them to Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. as the purſuer of blood drove the murtherer to the City of refuge, <hi>Joſhua</hi> 20.3. then the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> cannot be a covenant of grace. 2. If it was a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace with every particular perſon in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> this were to make them all to be their own ſaviours and redeemers; but this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, for with many of them God was diſpleaſed, and their car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſes fell in the wilderneſſe. 3. The faithfull amongſt them were ſaved by their faith in Chriſt crucified, which the braſen Serpent ſignified, and they did eat the ſame ſpirituall meat with us, and drink of the ſame ſpirituall drink, for they drank of the rock which was Chriſt, and thoſe that were prophane are ſaid to tempt Chriſt, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4.9. 4. It is plainly ſaid that they were in covenant with God before the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was given, for God is ſaid while they
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113996:6"/>were in <hi>Aegypt</hi> to remember his covenant and to have reſpect unto them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.23, 24, 25. and the Lord calls himſelf the God of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> and the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and bids them ſay to <hi>Pharoah, let my people go that they may ſerve me, and ſacrifice to the Lord their. God, and I will be to you a God, and ye ſhall be to me a people,</hi> which is the very tenour of the covenant of grace, ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6, 7, 8, 9. and 5.3. and 6, 7. but Mr. <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> (whom in reſpect of his great worth I much reverence, although in this particular point I diſſent from him till I beconvinced with more evidence of truth) ſaith the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> is a covenant of grace, becauſe it beares the name of covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.13. I anſwer, it beares that name from the old tenure when it was given to <hi>Adam</hi> for a covenant of works; but it will not follow that it is ſtill a covenant no more then the calling <hi>Rahab</hi> a harlot will conclude her ſtill to be a harlot, after her faith is ſo highly commended, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. but he ſaith it hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of a covenant, there be the parties God and Man, and it is written with penalties and promiſes.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, It was a covenant to <hi>Adam,</hi> therefore thoſe things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained to ſhew them their miſery by his fall, and thoſe that were not brought off by Chriſt were ſtill under that covenant and as yet never freed from it, then it had been a vain thing to give them that old bond as a covenant unto which they were ſtill bound and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for ever, then I ſay it was given them for thoſe forenamed ends, and not as a covenant.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith it was a covenant of grace becauſe God did not deale with them as abſolutely conſidered, but as their God, for to them belong the covenants, the giving of the Law and the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, God was in covenant with them before the Law at <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> was given, therefore the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> did not bind them as a covenant to obey it, or elſe lye under the penalty of it, and from this very text the giving of the Law is diſtinguiſhed from the promiſes, the firſt although given as a rule, yet bearing the name of covenant; and the latter they had many promiſes of Chriſt which is the Goſpell, declaring the covenant of grace; the Goſpell was preached to them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.2. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.6. <hi>John</hi> 8.56. then all this will not prove the Morall Law to be a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>His 2. Argument if it be conſidered the good things annexed to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113996:7"/>the covenant, then this at <hi>Sinai</hi> muſt be a covenant of grace, for at <hi>Si nai</hi> was remiſſion of ſinnes, and ſhewing mercy to thouſands, <hi>Ex.</hi> 20.5. I anſwer, it is true, to all thoſe that did obey the Law as a rule of righteouſneſſe, yet not for it, but becauſe they were in the covenant of grace before, for all grace and comfort flowes from the covenant made with Chriſt, and not from that made with <hi>Adam,</hi> nor from the copy of it given as a rule to <hi>Iſrael</hi> at <hi>Mount Sinai, grace and truth came by Jeſus Chriſt, John</hi> 1.16.</p>
            <p>His 3. Argument, if we conſider the duties commanded in the Law ſo generally taken, it muſt needs be a covenant of grace, for what is the meaning of the firſt Commandement, but to have one God in Chriſt to be our God by faith, I anſwer, it is true to thoſe that are in the covenant of grace before, but the copy of <hi>Adams</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant cannot reconcile them to God in Chriſt, that muſt be done by the covenant of grace, and being in that covenant of grace alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> may command us to walk accordingly, but ſaith he, ſhall we think that any can do the Law without any ſpot of ſin, or without the grace of God to pardon them? I anſwer no, for the Law was not given them and us for that end, for it was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the hand of a mediatour, and now God accepts of the will for the deed, and the preface hath relation to the covenant of grace going before; therefore although the Law be a perfect copy of the covenant of works, yet being given to another end it cannot diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null the covenant of grace that was confirmed before of God in Chriſt, nor make the promiſes of it of none effect, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. then this copy of the morall Law is not a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>His fourth Argument from the Ceremoniall Law all Divines ſay it was reduced to the Morall Law, ſo that ſacrifices were comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by vertue of the ſecond Commandement, and ſacrifices were E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangellicall and held forth remiſſion of ſins through the blood of Chriſt, I anſwer, thoſe that were in the covenant of grace before, and did by faith ſee Chriſt in thoſe ſacrifices, grant that Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> did command them to walk accordingly as being made ſubſervient to the covenant of grace, and ſo the poſitive Lawes of the Land are uſefull and ſubſervient to the covenant of grace, ſo that he who ſhall preſume either againſt mans Law or Gods Law, as now it is made uſefull to us, doth exceedingly aggravate his ſin, to treaſure up wrath to himſelfe againſt the day of wrath, although neither the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113996:7"/>Law of God nor man is the covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>His fifth Argument he ſaith will appear from the viſible ſeale to ratifie this covenant which you have heard was by ſacrifices and ſprinkling the people, which did ſignifie Chriſt as mediatour to this covenant. I anſwer, the covenant of works to <hi>Adam</hi> needed no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices for ſin as a ſeale of that covenant, and for the copy of it gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> was not given as a covenant but as a rule of life for thoſe already in covenant: Therefore the Morall Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> need no ſacrifices which were as ſeales to the covenant of grace, and not to that Law at <hi>Sinai,</hi> and thoſe ſeales were long before the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was given, <hi>Abels</hi> Lambe ſignified <hi>the Lambe of God that taketh away the ſins of the world, John</hi> 1.29. for Chriſt was then the true Lambe ſacrificed, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.8. now leſt any ſhould mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, there was three ſorts of Lawes publiſhed in writing at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> which were not written before, firſt, that eternall Morall Law in the 20. chap. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> now this was not only written for them but for us allſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. yea for Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels eternally, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89.103.20. not one title of this Law ſhall faile, and the Apoſtles do not ſeek to make void this Law, but do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.31. but then at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> there was the Judiciall Law given in the 21, 22, 23. chapters of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and that Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs no more to us then our Lawes of the Land belong to them any farther then they are grounded on the morall Law. 3. There was the Ceremoniall Law given in the 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. now this ceremoniall Law being in types and ſhadowes of Chriſt to come were all ended when Chriſt was once offered to beare the ſins of many, although the Prieſts ſtood daily miniſtring and offering oftentimes the ſame ſacrifices, but when Chriſt had offered one ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for ſins, for ever ſate down at the right hand of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28.10, 11, 12. ſo then thoſe ſacrifices were not ſeales of the morall Law, but of the ceremoniall which was their Goſpell in dark types and ſhadowes, ſhewing them Chriſt with whom the covenant of grace was made from all eternity, and that it is ſo, obſerve the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law was given with terrible thundrings and earthquakes, that the people durſt not come neare, but cryed, let not God ſpeak unto us leſt we dye, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.18, 19. but when the ceremoniall Law was given they ſaw the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and there was under his feet as it were a paved work of a Saphirſtone, and as it were the body of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113996:8"/>in his clearneſſe, alſo they ſaw God and did eat and drink, ſee <hi>Exodus,</hi> 24.3.4.10, 11. thus the Morall Law was given with dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and terors, and this with light and comfort, then the morall Law is not a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>His ſixt Argument, if the Law was the ſame covenant and the oath which God made to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> then it muſt needs be a covenant of grace, but ſaith he, God when he gave the Law made it an Argument of his love and grace to them, ſaying; <hi>if ye hearken to theſe judgements and do them that the Lord thy God ſhall keep unto thee the covenant and mercy which he ſwore unto thy Fathers, Deut.</hi> 7.12. I anſwer, if this Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> ſhould be the ſame which God ſwore to <hi>Iſaac,</hi> then the Law and Goſpell would be the ſame thing, but I need go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then this one text to confute it, where God ſaith, <hi>if ye hearken to theſe judgements, being the rule of their obedience, then God will keep with them the covenant made with their fathers before the Law at</hi> Sinai <hi>was given,</hi> this at <hi>Sinai</hi> is called judgments, that is called a covenant, this is called judgments in oppoſition to the other, being an oath and promiſes, then the copy of the morall Law given at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> for a rule of obedience was not a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>But then ſaith M. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> there are ſtrong objections againſt theſe Arguments from <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.14. and it ſeems they are too ſtrong for him, for I heare no more of them, only he ſaith if it ſhould be rigidly and univerſally true, then the Doctrine of Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians would prevaile, that there was no grace nor faith, nor nothing of Chriſt vouchſafed to the Jewes, but what neceſſity is there of this, Chriſt was held out to them by the brazen Serpent, <hi>John</hi> 3.14. and <hi>Moſes</hi> complains for their want of faith, ſaying, <hi>they are a fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward generation, a people in whom there is no faith, Deut.</hi> 32.20. and they were puniſhed at <hi>Meribah,</hi> becauſe they beleeved not, yea they could not enter into the promiſed laid becauſe of their unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.19. but then I ſay Chriſt was tendred by the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Law, and faith in Chriſt is required from that, and not from the morall Law, yet I will neither exclude the Law nor Goſpell, nor will I divide them in the working grace in the elect, for by the law we ſee our miſery, and by the Goſpell our remedy, and they are enemies to the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deny either in the work of a ſinners con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; but all this will not prove that the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113996:8"/>
            <p> But then he ſaith, as the law worketh death, ſo the goſpell to ſome is the ſavovr of death, and if Chriſt had not come then men had had no ſin, and they ſhall have greater judgements that deſpiſe Chriſt then they that deſpiſed the Law, and this effect is accidentall through our corruption, and then he ſaith that God doth not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe grace and juſtification in a legall way by that Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> but evangelically, but I ſay then it was by the ceremoniall Law, and not from the morall Law, or at leaſt the morall Law did ſhew them their miſery, and the ceremoniall Law ſhewed them Chriſt their on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remedy, then the morall Law is not a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He ſaith that the Apoſtle ſpeaks theſe derogatory paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages and they ſeem to be as well the ceremoniall law, yet all do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge here was Chriſt and grace held forth; but by his good leave, <hi>Paul</hi> was not willing to be found in his own righteouſneſſe which is of the law, but that which is of the faith of Jeſus Chriſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. becauſe that which comes only by the morall law is but our inherent righteouſneſſe, when as the other by the goſpell is not in us but in Chriſt, and imputed to us, and by this we ſtand juſt in the ſight of God, the one we have by the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and the other we have by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> then if theſe do but ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly differ let the Reader judge, and that other place <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13, 14. where it is ſaid the promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> was not to him and his ſeed through the law, but through the righteouſneſſe of faith, for if it had been by the law the promiſe of Chriſt or the covenant of grace had been void; ſo that here alſo is more then a ſeeming diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſo <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18. if the inheritance were by the law, it is no more of promiſe, if grace were had at <hi>Sinai</hi> it could not be had by the covenant of grace to <hi>Abraham</hi> made by promiſe, then are theſe but ſeeming derogatories? no they are ſuch objections that ſeem to be too ſtrong for him; therefore it ſtill holds good that the morall Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was no covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He ſaith it is true that the law is a killing letter to thoſe that take it without Chriſt, and ſo is the goſpell, but I would know how any can take Chriſt from the morall law at <hi>Sinai</hi> when as he was never tendred by that law, Chriſt only is tendred in his own covenant of grace made from all eternity, and the promiſes in Chriſt are yea and amen, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. but he ſaith if any had ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> your doctrine is but a killing letter and not a doctrine of life, he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113996:9"/>would have been judged a blaſphemer againſt the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> I anſwer, as the Law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was a rule to beleevers, if any man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed this Law he dyed without mercy, becauſe by Chriſt it was made a rule for them to walk by, and ſuch a one ſhewed plainly that he was not a believer, and ſo not in the covenant of grace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed before to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo then the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was a rule of life, but the goſpell is the chiefe inſtrumentall cauſe of life; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that ſins againſt the goſpell ſhall have the great puniſhment, yet all this will not make the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> to be a covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he ſaith we muſt retain that diſtinction of a large and a ſtrict ſence of the law, but I ſay let him take the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> as ſtrict or as large as he will, it is not a covenant of grace, and therefore can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtate a man in grace only, it is given both to them and us as a rule to walk by, and we ought ſtill to obey it ſo far as we are able, and yet not as a covenant of grace but as a rule of life.</p>
            <p>In the next place I ſhall prove that the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was not a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of works, if the Lord had ſet them upon a covenant of works this would have diſanul'd the covenant of grace given 430. years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and if ſalvation came by works it is no more of grace, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17.18. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. but ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> is the law againſt the promiſes of God, God forbid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. then the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was not a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of workes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> had been a covenant of works this were to make them their own ſavoiurs, but it was the happineſſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be ſaved by the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. then the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was not a covenant of works.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, If all mankind lye dead in ſin under the guilt and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of the covenant of works already, then they are uncapable of another covenant of works, but all men are dead in ſins, 1 <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.3.19. then the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was not given to <hi>Iſrael</hi> as a covenant of works, but as a rule of life to them, being in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace before.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, If <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a peculiar ſpeciall holy people to the Lord and yet born into the world, dead in ſin, uncapable of working, then this muſt needs be done by a covenant of grace, but they were ſuch a people, <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6. then not by working but by faith in that covenant of grace confirmed to <hi>Abraham</hi> 430. yeares before, they became ſuch a people and not by the law at <hi>Sinai.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:9"/>
            <p> Fifthly, If <hi>Iſrael</hi> was married to the Lord as the ſpous to the husband and in relation of children to their father, then this was done by the covenant of grace confirmed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> but <hi>Iſrael</hi> was ſuch a people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.5. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.19, 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.13. <hi>Iſa</hi> 49.15. then the law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was only a rule of life, but not a covenant of works, whereby to make themſelves ſuch a people.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, If the Lord had put them that were dead in ſins and under the curſe and penalty of the covenant of works already to work themſelves out of that miſery, by doing the works of that covenant, this had been no mercy at all to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but that law at <hi>Sinai</hi> was a great mercy to <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> he had not dealt ſo with any nation as to give them his lawes and Statutes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.18, 19. then it was not given to them as to <hi>Adam</hi> a covenant of works, but as a rule of life.</p>
            <p>Now ſome may ask why it is ſo frequent in the old Teſtament, <hi>doe this and live, and if ye keep my Covenant, then ye ſhall be a peculiar people unto me above all people, Exodus</hi> 19.5.6. I anſwer, it is no more then is ſaid in the new Teſtament, <hi>he that doth the will of my Father ſhall come to heaven, and he that keepeth my Commandements hath right to the tree of life, and ſhall enter into the holy City, the doers of the Law are bleſſed in the deed,</hi> ſee <hi>Mal.</hi> 7.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. <hi>James</hi> 1.25. 2. This doth not deny the doing of the law by a ſurety, for it is not ſaid that no other ſhall do it for thee, but do this either thy ſelfe or by a ſurety and thou ſhalt live. 3. There is an Evangelicall doing of the Law, when with our deſire and endeavour we obey the whole Law. 4. We muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it to be of thoſe in the covenant of grace, who do all in the ſtrength of Chriſt, and his perfect obedience to the law is imputed to them as if they had done it, and they obeying the law not as a covenant of works, but as a rule of life, and God accepting it as done by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and that perfectly, they that thus do the law ſhall live; yet this doth not make the morall Law to be a covenant of Works.</p>
            <p>Now ſome it may be will ſay there is more then two covenants made with mankind, for ſaith the Lord; <hi>behold the daies come that I will make a new covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and with the houſe of Judah,</hi> Jer. 31.31. then if it be a new covenant, it is neither the covenant of Workes with the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> nor the covenant of grace with the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> I anſwer, This promiſe is made to <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> at their return out of captivity, but ſuppoſe it is meant now ſince the coming of Chriſt, yet it amounts but to the ſame thing, which is a new diſcovery or a lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger manifeſtation of the covenant of grace made with Chriſt as media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor before the world began, which was firſt declared to <hi>Adam</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb facs="tcp:113996:10"/>after his fall, the ſeed of the woman ſhal break the Serpentshead, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. after that in proceſſe of time, <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> brought their offerings to the Lord, and <hi>Abels</hi> lambe did then tipifie the true Lambe of God that taketh away the ſins of the world, for he was ſlain from the beginning of the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.8. <hi>John</hi> 1.29. and God accepted <hi>Abels</hi> offring, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.3, 4. and God commanded <hi>Noah</hi> to take of clean beaſts and foules into the Ark by ſeavens, which was to ſacrifice to the Lord, and the Lord ſmelled a ſavour of reſt and ſaid in his heart, <hi>I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ourſe the ground for mans ſake,</hi> Gen. 7.2, 3.8.20, 21. now all this could not be ſo accepted but as they had faith in Chriſt the true ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; ſee their faith <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4.7. after this when the ceremoniall Law was written through the whole book of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and from the 24. of <hi>Exodus</hi> to the 32. then they ſaw God and did eat and drink, they ſaw the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> with comfort, and as it were the body of heaven in his clearneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.10, 11. that is; the covenant of grace was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted more clearly then formerly, after this the Lord makes known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that a Virgin ſhall bear a ſon, and call his name <hi>Imanuel,</hi> after this unto us a child is born, unto us a ſon is given, and the government ſhall be on his ſhoulders, it is ſo in reſpect of certainty, <hi>Iſa</hi> 17.14.9.6. for the covenant was made after the world began, after this a further manifeſtation in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> viſion, where the foure eſtates of Chriſt are lively ſet forth, his birth mean, he had the face of a man, 2. His life cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, he had the face of a Lyon. 3. In his death ſacrificed as an oxe. 4. In his aſcenſion like an Eagle, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.4. compared with <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.7. now theſe are the badges or mottoes of the foure Evangeliſts, for they did lively ſet forth the birth, life, death, reſurrection, and aſcenſion of Jeſus Chriſt, ſo that that this is the laſt and fulleſt manifeſtation of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace; and if when the ceremoniall law was written they did as it were <hi>ſee the body of heaven in his clearneſſe, Exod.</hi> 24.10. may not we ſay with <hi>Stephen</hi> when all the Church Officers are ſet in their places, <hi>now I ſee the heavens not only cleare, but opened, and Chriſt at the right hand of God, Acts</hi> 6.5.7.55. ſo then preaching of the Goſpel the higheſt and fulleſt manifeſtation of Chriſt in the covenant of grace which was made before the world began, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.2. and ſaith <hi>Paul, the preaching of Jeſus Chriſt was kept ſecret ſince the world began, but now is made manifeſt by the ſcriptures according to the command of God, to all nations for the obedience of faith,</hi> Rom. 16.25, 26.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay when the new covenant is made the old ſhall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. I anſwer, it is true, when Chriſt was ſacrificed he put an end to all ſacrifices and ceremonies that tipified him, crucified
<pb facs="tcp:113996:10"/>for ſins, all thoſe types and ſhadowes are done away, it is called the firſt covenant, and the manifeſting of Chriſt crucified, by the Hiſtory of the foure Evangeliſts is called the new covenant, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7, 8, 9. but ſome will ſay when the new covenant is made, God will write his lawes in their hearts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10.10.16. I anſwer, it is not ſaid that this ſhall only be done in the times after the Incarnation of Chriſt, although grace ſhall more abound then before his death, for as the Prieſtly office of Chriſt did ſhew it ſelfe moſt before his reſurrection by ſacrifices, ſo from thence his propheticall office is moſt ſeen, and ſhall be to the end of the world; ſo that the knowledge of God now ſhall be as the waters that cover the Sea, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9. and from thence his Kingly authority ſhall be ſeen clearly and ſhall never end, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.13. when all humane power is caſt down, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9. and his own Kingdome rendred up, by which he rules the Heathen with a rod of iron, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. in that day ſhall all be willing to obey him, or elſe made to ſuffer his will eternally; ſo then although more in number have the Law of God written in their hearts ſince the coming of Chriſt, yet the ſame thing was before, for ſaith <hi>David, I have hid thy Law in my heart that I may not ſin againſt thee,</hi> the Law of God is in his heart, none of his ſteps ſhall ſlide, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.3.119.11.40.8. then the preaching of the goſpell is not a new covenant, but a clear manifeſtation of the covenant of grace made with Chriſt before the world began.</p>
            <p>Now let us ſee what <hi>James Pope</hi> hath to ſay in his unveiling of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, of theſe two that are called covenants, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9. namely the ceremoniall law, pointing at Chriſt to come in all thoſe types and ſhadowes, and now the glorious preaching of the Goſpell declaring Chriſt to be already come and finiſhed the work of our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the differences between theſe covenants, with uſes and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of thoſe differences to our ſelves, and firſt by the way he ſaith to maintain ſomething ſtill that pointed at Chriſt to come when as he is already come, and hath done away thoſe things, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24, 25. muſt needs be Antichriſtian, but to men of underſtanding rather Judaiſme; for Papiſts do not uſe circumciſion nor ſacrifices, tipifying Chriſt to come, but then by his proof he ſeemes to mean that the morall Law was ended at the coming of Chriſt, being a Schoole-maſter to them before his coming; to bring them to Chriſt to be juſtified by faith; but I have proved that this morall Law of God is an eternall rule for Saints and Angels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89.103.20. and it is ſtill as a School-maſter to bring men out of liking with their corrupted eſtate, by reaſon of the miſery that attends them both in this world and in the world to come.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:11"/>
            <p> Then he ſpeaks of the ends why God made theſe covenants which is to take people neer unto himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.5, 6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.10. I anſ. Firſt, if he means the ceremoniall Law and our preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell; Theſe I have ſhewed to be but manifeſtations of the covenant of grace, now in that covenant God did intend his own glory in the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the elect, but if he ſpeak of that covenant of Works to <hi>Adam,</hi> they were created near unto God in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that covenant was made with them, which ſhould rather confirm then reconcile them to God, as the Angels were that never ſinned; but I paſſe on to his differences between theſe two covenants, which are as followeth;</p>
            <p>Firſt, In regard of the time when they were made, the firſt of them being made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> when God led them out of the land of <hi>Aegypt, Heb.</hi> 8.9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.4.31, 32. now theſe things I have anſwered already when I ſhewed the covenant of grace was made with Chriſt before the world was, and the covenant of works to <hi>Adam</hi> as ſoon as crerted, but if theſe covenants were not made before <hi>Iſrael</hi> went out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> how comes it to paſſe that all before Chriſt came in <hi>Adam</hi> dyed as well as we, and what is become of all thoſe holy men before his Incarnation, If the covenant of grace was not then made? again, would Chriſt firſt pay the purchaſe before he make the covenant, and if <hi>Adam</hi> condemn'd all mankind by his fall, what held off the wrath of God all that time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the covenant of grace as he would have it was made, we know the Angels that ſinned were immediatly caſt down, then notwithſtanding his cavilling, the firſt covenant was not made at their departure out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and if he ſpeak of the ceremoniall law, it is as old as <hi>Abell</hi> and <hi>Caine,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he ſaith ſome will object that this covenant of works is the ſame that God made with <hi>Adam,</hi> but he ſaith our ſtate is different from this, but I ſay no, for while <hi>Adam</hi> ſtood we ſtood, &amp; when he fell we fell with him; then he ſaith this covenant was to take ſome of the loſt ſeed of <hi>Adam</hi> near to himſelf, and the reſt were ſtrangers to the covenant of promiſe, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.12. I anſwer, it is true of the covenant of grace, and this manifeſtation of it was a means to bring them into that covenant.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith ſome will ſay, was it not made with <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 17. he anſwers, he had the promiſes of both covenants, and the types of both, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. and vertually he had both; but I ſay if he mean the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Law as a rule then it was not a covenant, or if he mean the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of works wherein he was born, all the promiſes are loſt by <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and only curſes and threatnings remain in it, ſo then he that hath
<pb facs="tcp:113996:11"/>a right to the covenant of grace muſt be freed from the covenant of works or elſe he cannot have it; no man can be under both the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants at once, which are as contrary as life and death, grace and ſin, the way to heaven and hell all at once; but then he ſaith the types and promiſes go before the thing tipifyed and promiſed, I grant it, for God promiſed eternall life before the world began, and the Lambe of God was tipifyed by <hi>Abels</hi> Lambe; then he ſaith the ſecond covenant was actually made at the death of the teſtator, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16, 17. but I have ſufficiently proved that this was made with Chriſt before the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; but if any ask what benefit thoſe had that were before this cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made, he ſaith they had the efficacy of his death by faith, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding Chriſt in the promiſes before any was made, but if his faith hath no better foundation, it will not ſtand in the fiery tryall, for what ground is there for faith before the covenant was made, it is preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to believe without a promiſe.</p>
            <p>His ſecond difference, the firſt covenant was made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the fleſh, the ſecond in relation to Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. it ſeems by him that neither was made with Chriſt immediatly, for both were made to men, although one hath relation to Chriſt, yet the foundation is men, and then to Chriſt, as the Papiſts themſelves will be the agents to take Chriſt as an inſtrument to ſave them, but the ceremoniall law and our preaching the Goſpell ſerve both to ſhew forth the covenant made with Chriſt eternally, they had divine ordinances, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. then not fleſhly.</p>
            <p>His third difference is in regard of the conditions of the covenants, the firſt ſaith, <hi>doe this and live,</hi> but this I have anſwered already that a ſurety is not here denyed, and there is an Evangelicalll doing the whole Law in their deſire and endeavour as a rule to them in the covenant of grace already, but ſaith he, the new covenant requires nothing by way of condition of the creatures part, and yet he ſaith the Lord will put his lawes in their mind, and write them in their hearts, what are thoſe but conditions, for then the covenant followes, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people, Jer.</hi> 31.33.</p>
            <p>His fourth difference, the promiſes of the firſt covenant are only of temporall things, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.1.10.15. <hi>Jer.</hi> 11.5. but the promiſes of the new covenant are all ſpirituall, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.9, 10, 11. but ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have eſtabliſhed my covenant with them, to give them the land of Canaan, and I will take you to me for a people, and I will be to you a God,</hi> Exod. 6.4.7. is here nothing but temporall things, and ſaith <hi>Paul God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe hath the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come,</hi> 1 Tim. 4.8. and if he mean the ceremoniall law it ſhewed them, Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:113996:12"/>if he ſpeak of the morall law it was not given them as a covenant, but as a rule of obedience.</p>
            <p>His fifth difference is between the mediators of theſe covenants, the mediator of the firſt he conceives to be <hi>Moſes</hi> from theſe ſcriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.25. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.11.14. <hi>Pſal,</hi> 106.23. but the mediator of the new covenant between God and man is Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. I anſwer, if he ſpeak of the morall law it was not given to them nor us as a covenant, but as a rule of life, and ſo they did reverence it at the hand of <hi>Moſes,</hi> repreſenting Chriſt the only mediator, for when Chriſt came, he took the Law in his firſt Sermon and gave it with his own hand, ſaying; <hi>you have heard thus, but I ſay thus;</hi> yet not as a covenant but as a rule of life, and if he mean the ceremonialI Law, <hi>Moſes</hi> did not at all mediate for it, we have but one mediator the man Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. and <hi>Moſes</hi> did no more but pray for the people as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and as many other men may do.</p>
            <p>His ſixt difference is between the bloods of the covenants, the firſt but the blood of Calves and Goates, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.19, 20. and yet called the blood of the covenant, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8. but the blood of the new covenant is the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. I anſwer, if he mean the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law that requires no blood at all, neither to <hi>Adam</hi> when it was a covenant, for he had no ſin; neither at <hi>Sinai,</hi> for then it was but as a rule to thoſe already in covenant, and for the ceremoniall law, the blood of calves and goates was no more the blood of that covenent, then wine is the blood of our Sacrament, for it did but ſignifie the blood of Chriſt, and when <hi>Moſes</hi> bids the people behold the blood of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8. he doth not mean the blood of calves and goates, but the blood of Chriſt which is called the blood of the covenant, ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.13.20.</p>
            <p>His ſeventh difference is in writing the law of the covenants, the firſt was written in tables of ſtone, <hi>Ex.</hi> 32.15, 16. but the law of the new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant in the heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25. I anſwer, as before the law that was written in tables of ſtone was the morall law, and was not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a covenant but as a rule of life to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and both the morall law and the Goſpell are written with paper and ink in the bible, and he that hath the law of God in his heart none of his ſteps ſhall ſlide, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.31. when men by nature do the things of the law, they ſhew ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of it in their hearts as a covenant of works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. but when it is written in the heart not as a covenant but as a rule of life, this is ſanctification.</p>
            <p>His eighth difference is in regard of the obſcurity of the one, and the
<pb facs="tcp:113996:12"/>plainneſſe of the other: I anſwer, it is true, the morall law was given with blackneſſe and darkneſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.21. when as the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall law in compariſon of it, was as it were the body of heaven in his clearneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.10. and now by preaching the Goſpell we doe not only ſee a clearneſſe of the heavens but heaven opened, and Chriſt at the right hand of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.56. they had but dark types and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of Chriſt, and now he hath manifeſted himſelf unto us, <hi>John</hi> 14.22. in this we do not differ, only he holds them to be two covenants, when as it is but a more dark and a more clear manifeſtation of the ſame covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>His ninth difference is about the worſhip that did appertain to theſe covenants, that which did belong to the firſt covenant did conſiſt of types and ſhadowes of good things to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. but the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the new covenant declares them to be already come, to this let my laſt anſwer ſuffice.</p>
            <p>His tenth difference is that the firſt covenant is done away, that the ſecond might be eſtabliſhed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13.10.9. this I grant, if he mean the dark ceremoniall law in types and ſhadowes of Chriſt, this is done away that the clear manifeſtation of Chriſt might remaine by preaching the Goſpell, but if he mean that the morall law that was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with blackneſſe and darkneſſe as he ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18. this I deny, for it is a rule of Saints and Angels eternally, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.80.103.20. ſo much in anſwer to his differences now let us ſee what uſes he makes of theſe differences.</p>
            <p>In the uſe of his firſt difference he ſaith if the firſt covenant was made when <hi>Iſrael</hi> returned out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> then all actuall ſin is not againſt the firſt covenant as ſome think, for then it ſhould be made with all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which he denyes from that text <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. and to be made before it was, and to be ſtill in being, whereas he ſaith it is done away. I anſwer, the firſt covenant being that of works, was made with the whole race of mankind in <hi>Adam,</hi> and while he ſtood all ſtood, but when he fell all the world became guilty before God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. for in <hi>Adam</hi> all dye, <hi>ver.</hi> 15.22. ſin and death paſſed upon all by his ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. then the firſt covenant was made before <hi>Iſraels</hi> going out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and all mankind are born under it, and all actuall ſin is againſt it only, when it was given as a rule of life in the hand of a mediator, it did more nearly concern them and not to other nations till they have it all in writing, as <hi>iſrael</hi> had, which may anſwer that text, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19.20. but then he denyes that all ſin is done away by Chriſt, and yet by and by he ſaith all thoſe ſacrifices were not ſufficient to do it, they muſt look beyond all
<pb facs="tcp:113996:13"/>thoſe things to Chriſt, and yet in his ſixt difference he ſaid the blood of calves and goates was the blood of the covenant; then he ſaith ſome hold that unbelief is the only ſin againſt the new covenant, and he hath nothing to the contrary; therefore I paſſe on to the uſe of his ſecond difference, where he ſaith if the firſt covenant was made with <hi>Iſrael</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh, and the ſecond with <hi>Iſrael</hi> after the ſpirit, then to affirme that Infants are holy by their parents, believing is to hold forth ſtill a covenant in the fleſh which he underſtands is to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh. I anſwer, he that denyes the doctrine of Chriſts Apoſtles, denyes Chriſt, but he denyes the doctrine of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith if but one of the parents be a beleever, the children are holy, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. then in all wiſe mens judgment <hi>James Pope</hi> denyes Chriſt to be come in the fleſh: to this he ſaith we are to mind the ſcope of the place, which was to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer a doubt, to wit; whether a beleeving husband might dwell with an unbelieving wife, his anſwer is they may, for elſe the children were unclean as under the firſt covenant, but ſee how this man contradicts himſelf, now he ſaith the Heathens were under the firſt covenant, which lie denyed before from that text <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. then he ſeems to grant it a thing out of queſtion, that if believers children dwell with their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, then they are holy; but if the Anabaptiſts grant this, why will they not baptize thoſe that dwell with their believing parents, but the truth is this, when the husband was converted to the Chriſtian faith and not the wife, or the wife and not the husband, and ſo baptized, it ſeems this was their great queſtion, ſhall my children be baptized? the anſwer is ſecretly implyed they may; for though thy husband or thy wife be an Infidell, yet being made one fleſh by marriage with a Chriſtian, they are ſanctified to a holy uſe, &amp; ſo the children being holy by this means, they are and ought to be baptized; now this is not a reall holineſſe, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet a part as the Elements from a common to a holy uſe, to enjoy the ordinances of the viſible Church, and <hi>Iſmaels</hi> poſterity being out of the Church were the ſeed of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.29. and thoſe in the viſible Church may be thus called holy, that is taken from a common to a holy uſe, as members of the viſible Church, although they have not reall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and by vertue of this holineſſe their children have a right to the viſible ordinances in the publike worſhip of the Chriſtian Church, then he runs into a large degreſſion, but I do not liſt to follow him, then he ſaith to hold a nation as <hi>England, Scotland, Germany, &amp;c.</hi> to be the Church of God in covenant, denyes Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and ſo is Antichriſtian, but I ſay again, to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh is Judaiſme, but not Antichriſtianiſme; again, if Chriſt ſent out his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles
<pb facs="tcp:113996:13"/>to teach and baptize or diſciple whole nations, then he that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth this is Antichriſt, for he oppoſeth all that is called God, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. but here this man oppoſeth Chriſt in his work, to diſciple and bring in nations to the Chriſtian Church; <hi>Ergo,</hi> he is Antichriſt: the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor propoſition none will deny, and the minor is proved in denying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny nation as <hi>England and Scotland,</hi> who have received the Chriſtan faith, to be the Church of God, but he ſaith the Jewes being under the old covenant were but one Church, and when the Chriſtian Church was ſet up, there were many Churches even in <hi>Judea,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.14. I anſwer, the ſeverall Congregations in <hi>Iſrael</hi> before Chriſt be called Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but being put together it is called a Congregation, for both theſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.2.4. and ſo in the new teſtament Churches make a Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1.7. then if he oppoſe, a nationall Church is rather Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian then they which plead for it againſt factions.</p>
            <p>The uſe of this 3. difference, if the conditions of the firſt covenant was <hi>do this and live,</hi> then this ſhewes us the reaſon why God dealt ſo ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them in outward things when they ſinned againſt him, becauſe it was according to the conditions of his covenant with them. I anſwer, thoſe that are ſtill under <hi>Adams</hi> covenant are ſtill liable to all kind of puniſhments, whether Jewes or Chriſtians, yet it will not follow that all who are puniſhed in outward things are ſtill under that covenant of works, although they may and are ſtill under the Law given at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> yet not as a covenant but as a rule of life, and for ſin againſt it may be puniſhed in outward things in love, to reclaime them from their ſinne.</p>
            <p>Then he ſaith the people of the new covenant live to doe, and not doe to live, they do not act to be kept in Gods favour, that ſo they may acknowledge to the praiſe of God, that all is of grace electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5, 6. and Chriſt dyed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. and juſtified, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.7. to believe, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.27. and hope, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16. and ſaved, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8.9. all of grace to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.6. all theſe I grant are of grace, but to ſay we may not act to be kept in Gods favor is not at all againſt the grace of God ſaith <hi>Elihu, if I ſhould give flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring titles to men my maker would ſoon take me away, Job</hi> 33.21, and ſaith <hi>David, if I regard iniquity in my heart, God will not heare my prayer,</hi> Pſal. 66.18. therefore one of them durſt not ſlatter, nor the other hide ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity in his heart, leſt he ſhould loſe the favour of God: the ſpouſe in the <hi>Canticles</hi> having ſmarted for her negligence to Chriſt, when ſhe found him held him faſt, <hi>Can.</hi> 3.4. then did ſhe not act to be kept in his favour, and <hi>David</hi> prayed for it, ſaying; <hi>O viſit me with that favour thou
<pb facs="tcp:113996:14"/>beareſt unto thy people,</hi> Pſal. 106.4. then he ſaith; to hold forth works as the conditions of the firſt covenant denies Chriſt to be come in the fleſh: all this I grant, and he that obeyes the Law as a covenant of works is to deny Chriſt, but to obey the morall Law as a rule of righteouſneſſe doth very wel conſiſt with the covenant of grace, &amp; as many as obey this rule, <hi>peace be on them and mercy,</hi> Gal. 6.16. let us walk by the ſame rule, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.16. the tables of the covenant were in the Ark, which ſignified Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his 4. difference, if the promiſes of the new covenant are only ſpirituall, then this may ſilence all thoſe that walk not with them in the publike way, but I deny the promiſes of the new covenant to be only ſpirituall, for godlineſſe hath the promiſe of the life that now is, and of that which is to come, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. and they are to blame that will not walk with them that do obey the rule: but thoſe are not Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts who deſpiſe the rule and will not admit any poore into their Congregations, and receive mony for admittance to my knowledge, but they have a ſalve for this ſore, they will tell you that the mony which maintains their Miniſter is ſpirituall, then he is troubled that they are called Sectaries, and that any ſhould run or write to Magiſtrates to have them put to death for denying their authority, writing ſtories of them in <hi>Germany,</hi> as if all were ſuch here, then he falls of praiſing of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts in <hi>England,</hi> who are in the field with their lives in their hands, to maintain a lawfull Magiſtracy, exceedingly blaming thoſe that diſcover their wicked lives, then he returns to his own faction, calling them the people of the new covenant, and tels them what they muſt ſuffer, then he ſeems to envy our Churches happineſſe and outward bleſſings atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, ſaying, their Miniſters are Gentlemen, and muſt have tythes of all mens charge and labour, all which brings them under the firſt cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, which is Antichriſtian, you ſee his Logick, and I think you will judge it not worth anſwering, then he comforts them in the new covenant againſt falling away, ſaying, if God have writ his Law in their heart, who ſhall raize it out? if God have pardoned their ſins, who ſhall lay them to their charge? if God will not remember them who ſhall call them to mind? but what of this, <hi>Iſrael</hi> had this promiſe made to them at the return out of captivity as well as to us, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34.32.40. yet if he had meant that firſt covenant to be made to <hi>Adam</hi> and this to Chriſt, it had been the truth, for <hi>Adam</hi> brake his, but Chriſt who is both God and Man cannot ſin; therefore thoſe in his covenant although before his coming in the fleſh, they could not fall away, yea the ſame perſon <hi>Adam,</hi> although he fell from the covenant of works, yet when he beleeved in the promiſed ſeed
<pb facs="tcp:113996:14"/>which was Chriſt, he could not fall away: then to be kept from falling is not peculiar to us, but as a priviledge of all beleevers ever ſince the promiſed <hi>Meſſias</hi> to <hi>Adam,</hi> for then by his faith he was admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the covenant of grace.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his ſift difference, if the covenant, of which Chriſt and not <hi>Moſes</hi> is the mediator, be the better covenant, then to have any other mediator beſides is to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and ſo is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian. I anſwer, this is but courſe logick to grant that <hi>Moſes</hi> is a mediator, and to ſay he that hath any other then Chriſt denies his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the fleſh and is Antichriſtian, happy is he that condemneth not himſelf in that thing which he alloweth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.22. but I ſay it was not a covenant but a rule for thoſe in covenant which <hi>Moſes</hi> received for the people, and in that alſo he did but tipify Chriſt, who as ſoon as he entred into the mediatorſhip, at leaſt to manifeſt it, he in his firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon gave them the law in his own name, ſaying; <hi>you have heard thus, but I ſay thus, Mat.</hi> 5. but then he believes ſo long as Chriſt appears riſen Chriſt for us, and continueth his mediatorſhip, theſe in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God ſhall ſo continue, but he ſeems again to deny this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to thoſe before his reſurrection.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his ſixt difference, if the blood of Chriſt and not the blood of beaſts is the blood of the new teſtament; then here is the priviledge of Saints, the blood of the firſt Teſtament did only purify the fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.13. but the blood of Chriſt purgeth the conſcience from dead works to ſerve the living God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. I anſwer, from this very text where Chriſt took the cup and ſaid, <hi>this is my blood, Mat.</hi> 26.28. meaning the wine in the cup, but that wine cannot purge the conſcience no more then the blood of beaſts, which ſignified the blood of Chriſt to come, to their faith, as the wine in the Sacrament ſignifies the blood of Chriſt already ſhed for many, then he ſpeaks highly of their priviledge, ſo that now for the people of God to mourn for ſin, as under ſin is ſinfull; but here we may ſee this man who would be thought to be for Chriſt, doth flatly oppoſe and contradict Jeſus Chriſt, who would have us mourn for ſin, with this motive, they are bleſſed that mourn, for they ſhall be comforted, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4. but ſaith this man, to mourn for ſin as under ſin is ſinfull, only he hath left here a ſtarting hole as under ſin; here I grant that they are not under the raigning power of ſin, but yet many a dear child of God hath a law in his members that leads him captive to the law of ſin, <hi>Rom,</hi> 7.23. and ſo they are under ſin as under a Tyrant, but he ſaith this undervalues the blood of Chriſt as if it did need to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up yearly. I anſwer, although we are wholly juſtified, yet we are
<pb facs="tcp:113996:15"/>not wholly ſanctified, although our ſins be pardoned, yet they are not fully taken away in this world; then he ſaith to lye under the guilt of ſin hinders duty, I grant it, but the guilt is taken away, though not the being of ſin, and as grace growes ſin dyes, and he that is mortally dead is freed from ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his ſeventh difference, if the law of the firſt covenant was written in tables of ſtone, and law of the new covenant in the fleſhly table of the heart, then we are to rekon a Nation not to be in cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, and nations aſſuming to themſelves title and practice of Churches is Antichriſtian, but this I have anſwered to his uſe of the ſecond difference.</p>
            <p>But then he ſaith ſome will ſay that the inviſible Church doth conſiſt of Saints, but the viſible Church now hath ſome as bad as among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> he anſwers, then they will leaven them if they be not caſt out, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.6, 7.1. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.20. when they are known, this I grant, and I hope there will be a courſe taken with ſuch ere long if that will pleaſe him, but I doubt it will not, for he ſaith thoſe Nations that call themſelves Gods Churches are the waters that carry the whore, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.15. but this ſeems to be ſtrange doctrine, when Chriſt ſent his Apoſtles to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and baptize all Nations, if but one of thoſe Nations ſhould come in, upon their teaching, then it would be the waters that carry the whore, thus while he cryes whore, himſelfe is defil'd with <hi>Babilons</hi> whoredomes, and joynes with them in oppoſing Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his 8. difference, if the new covenant be ſo plain, and full of light, then let the people of it labor to walk as children of the light, and ſhew forth the praiſes of him that hath called us out of darkneſſe into his marvellous light, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. I anſwer, as before it was the morall law that was given with terror and thick darkneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.18.21. but not as a covenant but as a rule of life to thoſe in covenant, and when the ceremoniall Law was written they ſaw in compariſon of the times before, as it were the body of heaven in its clearneſſe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.4.10, 11. although thoſe types and ſhadowes were dark, compared with our clear manifeſtotion; then he ſaith the note that the Scripture gives to know if they be in the light is this, if they love the brethren, meaning Anabaptiſts, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7. and thoſe that deſire to have them impriſoned, baniſhed, or hanged, is from the dark ſpirit of Antichriſt, who ſay, let us fill all preſſes and make all pulpits ring, and poſſeſſe the Parliament, City and Kingdome againſt the ſects, &amp;c. and when Presbyterian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters cry continually to God, and the Magiſtrate, for fire from heaven we may ſafely conclude that this is from the dark ſpirit of Antichriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:113996:15"/>for God under the old Teſtament appointed, that for many offences men ſhould be put to death, as <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.36. but now to cut off by excommunication except for hereſie, and that under two or three witneſſes, but I ſay again that thoſe under the old Teſtament were in the ſame covenant of grace as we, though not under the ſame diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of it, and the new Teſtament is but the old fulfilled, and the old Teſtament is but the new in the promiſe, and they and we have all one heart &amp; one way to fear the Lord for ever, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39. but then he ſaith that the <hi>Preſbyterians</hi> will ſay they have more then two or three wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to prove their hereſie, but he ſaith that cannot be, unleſſe they be infallible, for their own intereſt blinds their eyes, and the whole buſineſſe is in their own hands that are parties, witneſſes, and judges, then it is not likely they ſhould acknowledge that to be truth which their ſuppoſed adverſaries hold, but will condemne it for Hereſy. I anſ. if their intereſt be ſo, as that their ſalvation or damnation lyes upon it, then it behoves them to give right judgment, which if it did not ſo concern them, it were more to be feared that they would not judge rightly of truth and Hereſie, but then he falls into a boaſting what the Sectaries have done, and railing againſt our Miniſters for their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Parliament with dedicatory Epiſtles, Sermons, and Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for power to ſuppreſſe them, which is not worth the anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his ninth difference, if the worſhip of the firſt covenant held out Chriſt to come, and the new covenant declares Chriſt to be already come, then it teaches us that to hold out any part of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip now is to deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, and ſo is Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; now here he ſhould tell us what be thoſe types and ſhadowes of Chriſt to come that ſtill we obſerve, and it ſeems they are theſe from his words following, their worſhip was tyed to one nation and to one place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.19, 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.5, 6. but how dare this man affirme that we hold that God ought to be worſhipped no where but in <hi>England,</hi> nor but in one place in <hi>England,</hi> when as we hold that God is worſhipped as well in other Nations as in this, and in many hundred places in this Kingdome, as in <hi>London;</hi> then he ſaith their worſhip was carnall, from that text <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. where it is ſaid that they were ordinances of divine ſervice, for they were all inſtituted by God himſelf, and all was done as the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 40. yet if he ſpeak of thoſe ordinances as they were uſed by thoſe that had not faith, I grant they were carnall to them, and ſo are our
<pb facs="tcp:113996:16"/>Sacraments to thoſe that have no faith in the thing ſignified by them, and to ſay ours are to be performed ſpiritually, ſo was theirs to them that ſaw the blood of Chriſt, which is the blood of the everlaſting covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.13.20. the thing ſignified by the blood of beaſts, <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.8.</p>
            <p>But then he ſaith, the people of God queſtion how a whole nation may be compeld to publike worſhip now, which was done in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe they were Gods people in covenant. I anſwer, this need not to be the queſtion of Gods people who are in covenant, for by his own confeſſion their caſe is the ſame as it was with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> then if Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts be ſuch, this need not to offend them, but prophane perſons, they indeed may queſtion what right they have, and fear to come too without a wedding garment, but he ſaith this will not make them hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, but I ſay it is not the command of God nor man that makes them hypocrites, but it is from their own wicked hearts, that will not obey thoſe commands, but he is afraid to come to our aſſemblies leſt he ſhould deny Chriſt to be come in the fleſh, which they do that obey the Magiſtrates command in coming to the publike worſhip of Chriſt, now <hi>Shiloe</hi> is come the Magiſtrates have no relation to the Church, their power is only in things appertaining to this life, and in thoſe things ſaith he we are to obey for conſcience ſake, when as it is required of Kings and all in authority, <hi>that thoſe under them may lead not only a quiet and peaceable, but a godly life,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.2. but this hath been ſufficiently anſwered by many.</p>
            <p>But he ſaith that if we object that then every man may do what is right in his own eyes, his anſwer is only this, if Magiſtrates be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to rule the nations, and Chriſt to order the affaires of his Kingdome, then the objection is reſolved, but this he cannot prove, that Chriſt is confin'd only to rule his Church, <hi>for when God raiſed him from the dead he ſet him at his own right hand far above all principalities and powers, might and dominion, and every name that is named both in this world and in the world to come, and put all things under his feet, and gave him to be the head over all things to his Church,</hi> Ephe. 1.20.21, 22. neither are Magiſtrates confined ſo to rule the State, as to have no relation to the Church, but to be as a guard to it, and to puniſh the diſturbers of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>The uſe of his laſt difference, if the Lord have taken away the firſt that he might eſtabliſh the ſecond, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.9. then this ſhould teach us to take heed that we do not go about to eſtabliſh againe that which
<pb facs="tcp:113996:16"/>God hath taken away, as all thoſe do which go about to bring into the worſhip of God the rights of the firſt covenant, this is indeed to give the ſpirit of God the lye, for in effect, they ſay the firſt covenant is beſt, when as the ſpirit of God ſaith the ſecond is beſt, being eſtabliſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better promiſes. I anſwer, Chriſt and all his benefits were then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and is any thing better then Chriſt and his benefits, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.8.16. ſo then the things promiſed were not better, but the manifeſtation or diſcovery now is better; the promiſes of grace were ſeal'd to them by the blood of beaſts, the type of Chriſts blood, and to us the promiſes of grace are ſeal'd by his own blood, but Chriſt and his benefits were the ſame both to them and us.</p>
            <p>Then he is perſwaded that each godly heart longs for the utter ruine of Antichriſt, which will be compleated ſo ſoon as this is generally ſeen, that the upholding of the firſt covenant is the upholding of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, for the Apoſtle admires that in as much as Chriſt was crucifyed, and ſo clearly held forth among them, which did put an end to all the rights of that covenant, that they ſhould be ſo bewitched as to bring them in again; but here I would know of him who it is that ſeeks to bring in circumciſion or any of their ceremonies which he ſeems to charge upon us without proof, becauſe the <hi>Galathians</hi> were bewitched with thoſe beggerly elements which we have not the leaſt ſhadow of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then he ſaith circumciſion was the ſigne of that covenant that did ſo deceive them, for if ye be circumciſed Chriſt ſhall profit you nothing, ye are debters to the whole law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2, 3. I anſwer with M. <hi>Perkins</hi> on theſe words, that circumciſion muſt be conſidered according to the circumſtance of time three waies; before Chriſt it was a Sacrament and ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt apprehended by faith, <hi>Rom</hi> 4.1. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of Chriſt it was a dead ceremony, yet ſome uſed it as a thing indifferent till the deſtruction of the Temple, but afterwards it was a deadly ceremony, and ceaſed to be a thing indifferent, ſo then, although it would be to us a renouncing of Chriſt, yet to the <hi>Jewes</hi> it was a Sacrament or ſeal of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt to their faith as our Sacraments do to us; thus the <hi>Jewes</hi> that believed were under the covenant of grace as well as we, although not under the ſame manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of it, they had the glad tydings of Chriſt in the promiſe, and we in the performance, their promiſes are ceaſed in our performances, and their types and ſhadowes ceaſed when Chriſt the ſubſtance came, their ceremonies were goſpell to them to ſhew them Chriſt, but theſe ceremonies are now worn out and are but beggerly Elements to us, they ſaw as it were the body of heaven, in its clearneſſe, by thoſe ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
<pb facs="tcp:113996:17"/>but we cannot ſee at all with them; thus their Goſpell is ceaſed to us, but our preaching and declaring Chriſt to be already come, is that everlaſting Goſpell preached by men and Angels in the midſt of heaven for ever, ſaying, <hi>fear God and give glory to him, and worſhip him that made the Heaven and Earth, and Sea, and Fountain of waters,</hi> Rev. 14.15, 16. and we ſhall then ſing the ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> as well as the ſong of the Lambe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. that is, we ſhall be as cheerfull in our duty to the morall law being a rule of righteouſneſſe, as to extoll and praiſe the Lord for his mercies, ſo then although the ceremoniall law be cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet the morall law abideth eternally, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.20.119.89. not as a covenant of grace, nor as a covenant of works, but as a rule of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, for <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote all the words of the Lord touching the ceremoniall law, <hi>Ex.</hi> 24.3, 4. and after that the Lord called <hi>Moſes</hi> up into the Mount, and there he gave him the tables of ſtone, and a law and Commandements which himſelf had written, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. to this end, to be a rule of righteouſneſſe, that thou maiſt teach them their duty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had ſeen the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> reconciled to them, <hi>ve.</hi> 10, 11. now the righteous being in the covenant of grace, ſhall enjoy the good things of it, and that eternally, when as the wicked being ſtill under the covenant of works, ſhall ſuffer the miſery and lye under the penalty of it eternally.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay the yoake of Chriſt is eaſie, and his burden is light, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.11. when as the law was a yoake which neither our fathers nor we are able to beare, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. therefore they were not in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, nor under the yoake of Chriſt. I anſwer, it was the ſame covenant of grace with ours, although not the ſame way adminiſtred unto them, circumciſion was a ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of faith to them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. yet a very heavy burden to fleſh and blood, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.25. and baptiſme an eaſie ſervice is come in the place of it, and ſo their Paſſeover was very chargeable to ſacrifice ſo many of their cattel; this we are eaſed of, and now the Lords Table requires but little of our eſtate, ſo alſo they had long and tireſome Journies to come to the Paſſeover at <hi>Jeruſalem, Pſal.</hi> 84.6, 7. when as now God accepts of our Paſſeover or Sacrament neare our own homes; ſo then Jewes and Chriſtians have the ſame covenant, only their burden of adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is taken off and made eaſie, for which we are exceedingly bound to praiſe the Lord and that for ever.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 16. line. 20. after read before, p. 32. r. is the higheſt, p. 20. l. 8. reverence, r. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, l. 15. r. leave out many, p. 21. l. 37. all, read alſo, the, r. their, riſen, r. ariſen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:17"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113996:18"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have lived an unworthy Miniſter in the ſame town with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of this Treatiſe theſe ſix and twenty years, and have been a conſtant obſerver and admirer, as of her other eminent gifts, ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of (thoſe which give the higheſt luſtre to them all) her hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble piety and charity. And (if I miſtake not) this <hi>Deborah</hi> doth here preſent unto thee in theſe her labours Bee-like a ſting and hony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd. Hony-ſweet inſtructions, counſels and exhortations gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of ſeverall flowres growing in Gods Paradiſe, tending to all ſorts of good husbandry, and alſo ſharp ſtings of reproof againſt all kinds of unthriftineſs, not ſparing the worſt of them, our Church-dividing Errours in theſe times. Who knows, but that, after the lightnings of ſo many worthy <hi>Barak's,</hi> and thundrings of ſo many powerfull <hi>Boanergeſſes</hi> both from the Pulpit and Preſſe, againſt theſe Troublers of our Iſrael, the Lord may be pleaſed to make ſome of theſe <hi>Siſera's</hi> fall by the hand and pen of a woman? Firſt read, then judge: and (as <hi>Barnabas</hi> did at <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 11.23.) when thou haſt ſeen the grace of God, be glad and ſay, <hi>The Lord be magnified,</hi> who (as he may do what he will with his own, ſo) hath given ſuch gifts to a woman, the fruits whereof ſhee here by her private pains ſends forth with her earneſt deſire for the glory of God, and the publike good. Which is alſo the hearty prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thy Chriſtian friend and well-wiſher in the Lord,</hi> Robert Cade.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <p>REader, in this Tract as in a former by her written, thou mayeſt find verified, eminency of gifts, humility of ſpirit, elegancy of ſtyle, ſoldity of matter, height of fancy, depth of judgment, cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of apprehenſion, ſtrength of reaſon, all ſweetly met together and truly (as well as piouſly) improved for the mayntenance of the old truths of Jeſus Chriſt, againſt the new errours of theſe times, by the Phoenix of this age, this rare and precious Gentlewoman, the envy and glory of her ſex.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
